A Guide to the Malcolm Bell Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Malcolm Bell Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13701
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions apply under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.)
Acquisition
This collection was transferred from Malcolm Bell at Brooks Hall to Special Collections Library at the University of Virginia on August 16, 2006.
Biographical/Historical Information
Malcolm Bell, a professor emeritus of classical archaeology at the University of Virginia, received a Bachelor's of Art, and a Ph.D (1972) from Princeton University, graduating cum laude with a degree in English, and studying classical archaeology. As a student, he participated in archaeological field work at Aphrodisias (1961-1963) and Morgantina (1967-1968). He received two pre-doctoral fellowships (Fulbright 1968-1969) and American Academy in Rome (1968-1970). His dissertation was on "The Terracottas Rome and Sicily," which was later published as the beginning of a series, "volume 1 Morgantina Studies," (1977) and later he became the co-editor of the series. He was the director of the University of Virginia excavations at Sicily where he travelled annually for field work at the excavation site of Morgantina, teaching students and colleagues from around the world.
Bell joined the faculty at the University of Virginia in 1971 as an Assistant Professor. He was promoted to full professor in 1986. His scholarly career centered on colonial Greek archaeology. He also studied western Greek terracottas which led to his work on Aegean classicism. He received a National Endowment of the Humanities grant for this work in 1977.
He is a fellow of the American Academy in Rome and has held a Guggenheim Fellowship. He served as A. W. Mellon Professor both at the American Academy in Rome (1991-1992, 1993-1996) and the Center for Advanced Study in the Visual Arts at the National Gallery of Art (1998-2000) He served as editor of Memoirs of the American Academy in Rome and has published articles on the Motya charioteer, athletic dedications in Sicily, and Greek bronze choreutes in Copenhagen. From 2002-2006 he served as Vice President for Professional Responsibilities for the Archaeological Institute of America. He has also served as advisor to the Minestero dei Beni e le Attivita Cultrali of Italy and oversaw the repatriation to Italy of the acrolithic sculptures from Morgantina (2008). He was awarded a Citizenship award by the town of Aidone, Sicily in 2008.
In addition to his archaeological work, and his teaching, he served the University as department chairman (1978-1985) and by actively participating in a variety of committees concerned with student residential life, playing a major role in the establishment of the university's first residential college.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the professional and academic papers of Malcolm Bell, professor emeritus of archaeology and former chairman of the Art Department at the University of Virginia. The collection covers the dates 1963; 1970-1992 and is 1,673 items, 6 hollinger boxes and 2.5 linear feet. There is correspondence with his colleagues in the fields of archaeology and art history, and documents from various academies and institutions. Most of the papers are related to his teaching and administrative work at the University of Virginia. Included is Faculty Senate meeting minutes, policies, and information from the committees that he served, such as the Committee of Residence Life.
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically by topic. Correspondence is arranged chronologically by year. (Letters of recommendation under confidential are in alphabetical order by last name)The collection is divided into two series, the work of Malcolm Bell in archaeology, and his teaching and administrative work at the University of Virginia.
Contents List
  Series I: Archaeology
  - 1984-1988 American Academy in Rome, 12 items (Box-folder 1:1)
    There are minutes, treasurer's report and information about a symposium on archaeological work being done in Morgantina
  - 1971-1978 American Federation of Arts, 12 items (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 1984-1985 Appraisals, 18 items (Box-folder 1:3)
    There are photocopies of art objects and letters about their identification and value
  - 1979-1988 Archaeological Institute of America, 15 items (Box-folder 1:4)
    There are minutes and financial information for the organization.
  - 1985-1989 Archaeology Sicily (Morgantina), 43 items (Box-folder 1:5)
    There is mostly correspondence from students and colleagues about participating in the excavation at Morgantina. Much of the correspondence is written in Italian. Ernesto De Miro is a frequent correspondent. Also included is a contract for a rental house in Morgantina.
  - 1977-1988 Conferences, 23 items (Box-folder 1:6)
    Included is information about the Middle Atlantic Symposium and Abstract Expressionism Idea & Symbol Conferences
  - 1986; n. d. Family Correspondence, 14 items (Box-folder 1:7)
    There are letters from his wife, Ruthie, his children and other family members
  - 1978-1980 General Correspondence, 17 items (Box-folder 1:8)
    Correspondents include Margaret "Maggie" Ellen Mayo, William Rasmussen, Ruth Latter, and Marion Stocker
  - 1981-1983 General Correspondence, 30 items (Box-folder 1:9)
    George Sensabaugh, William Rasmussen, Ernesto De Miro, Paul M. Peatross, Jr., William A. P. Childs, and Margaret Ellen Mayo
  - 1984-1985 General Correspondence, 30 items (Box-folder 1:10)
    Correspondents include Ninina Cuomo de Caprio, David S. Reese, Angelika Schmiegelow Powell, George Cromer, and Ernesto De Miro. Most of the correspondence is about participating in the excavation at Morgantina
  - 1986 General Correspondence, 16 items (Box-folder 1:11)
    Included is a letter from Joanna Hitchcock about the Princeton University Press accepting Bell's book on Morgantina. There is also a letter about plans for a film about Morgantina and letters of congratulations to Professor Bell.
  - 1987 General Correspondence, 24 items (Box-folder 1:12)
    Correspondents include Barbara Barletta and Ninina Cuomo di Caprio
  - 1988 General Correspondence, 40 items (Box-folder 1:13)
    Correspondents include Stephen R. Zwirn, Margaret Milhous, Joanna Hitchcock, Ernesto De Miro, and Ninina Cuomo Di Caprio. Included in the correspondence is advice from Professor Bell about Greek objects, receipt of galley proofs for Bell's article to the American Journal of Archaeology, work on his manuscript ("Morgantina Studies II,") and a grant from the National Endowment of the Humanities
  - 1989 General Correspondence, 21 items (Box-folder 1:14)
    Correspondents include Hugh P. Kelly, Claire Lyons, and Patricia Gilkison. Included are congratulations to Professor Bell for winning a Guggenheim award
  - n. d. General Correspondence, 14 items (Box-folder 1:15)
  - 1991 Georgia Historical Society, 1 item (Box-folder 1:16)
  - 1988-1991 Grant Proposals, 10 items (Box-folder 1:17)
    Need to remove social security numbers
  - 1971-1974 Green Springs, 51 items (Box-folder 1:18)
    There is correspondence from Frederick Hartt with Virginia Governors Linwood Holton and Mills E. Godwin expressing strong opposition against Holton's decision to build a prison at Green Springs in Louisa County, Virginia. Included is a petition to preserve the land, letters to the Cavalier, Daily, the Richmond Times-Dispatch, The Daily Progress, The Washington Star, and The New York Times.. There are also letters from the Governors and staff (Alexander "Sandy" Gilliam). Hartt also wrote to former First Lady, Mrs. Richard Nixon.
  - n. d. Lecture Evaluations, 2 items (Box-folder 2:1)
    Completed surveys about societies and their facilities for lecturing
  - 1988 Lecture Notes, 3 pages (Box-folder 2:2)
    There are random lecture notes about slides shown in an introductory class during the Fall of 1988
  - n. d. Miscellaneous, 13 items (Box-folder 2:3)
    There are random notes, photocopies of images from [Morgantina,] a paper by Richard T. Arndt, a report on computers by John L. Pfaltz, and children's schoolwork including a colorful drawing.
  - n. d."Morgantina Studies II: The Coins" Theodore Buttrey, # items (Box-folder 2:4)
    There is an outline of comments and a list of errors related to "Morgantina Studies II"
  - 1973-1974 Museum Purchases, 12 items (Box-folder 2:5)
    The are photographs and photocopies of museum items and correspondence about purchasing decisions
  - 1988 Newspaper Clippings, 29 items (Box-folder 2:6)
    Included are articles about the authenticity of museum pieces and random articles of interest to Professor Bell
  - 1982-1988 Papers given, 5 items (Box-folder 2:7)
    Included are papers by Jeffrey L. Hantman, Malcolm Bell, (in Italian) Charles E. Brownell, and Claire L. Lyons. There are other papers by unnamed authors
  - 1987 Papers given, 4 items (Box-folder 2:8)
    Included are papers by Robin Fox, Lars Karlsson, Professor D. Devereux, and other papers by unnamed authors.
  - n. d. State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) Equipment Trust, 28 items (Box-folder 2:9)
    Included is correspondence between the State Universities and SCHEV concerning funding for the arts
  - n. d. Theatre Restoration Proposal, 6 pages (Box-folder 2:10)
    Handwritten notes in Italian
  Series II: UVA
  - n. d. Art Department Accreditation, 2 items (Box-folder 2:11)
    Accreditation forms
  - 1973-1988 UVA Archaeological Programs, 20 items (Box-folder 2:12)
    Correspondents include Robert D. Cross, Arthur F. Stocker, Robert O. Graham, Jr., Frederick Hartt, Harry J. Dell, James F. Childress, David C. Benjamin, Steve Plog, Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., and John H. Humphrey (Tunisia controversy)
  - 1974-1977 Art Department Correspondence, 131 items (Box-folder 2:13)
  - 1978-1979 Art Department Correspondence, 110 items (Box-folder 2:14)
  - 1980-1988 Art Department Correspondence, 55 items (Box-folder 3:1)
  - 1984-1988 Art Department Exams, 3 items (Box-folder 3:2)
  - 1973-1977 Art Department Expenses, 21 items (Box-folder 3:3)
    Requisition orders for telephone and correspondence about financial needs and estimates
  - 1976-1979; 1988 Art History Department Faculty, 46 items (Box-folder 3:4)
    Included are the minutes of the Art History Faculty, memos to faculty members, and faculty assignments to committees
  - 1972-1990 Art Department Fellowships, 6 items (Box-folder 3:5)
    There is information about the Dr. M. Aylwin Cotton Fellowships
  - n. d. Art Department Graduate and Undergraduate Programs, 40 items (Box-folder 3:6)
    There is information about curriculum, and written proposals for changes in University programs
  - 1979-1989 Art Department Receipts, 44 items (Box-folder 3:7)
    Receipts from airplane tickets, hotels, travel, and art object purchases
  - 1970-1988 Arts and Sciences, 18 items (Box-folder 3:8)
    Arts & Sciences report on historical data of degrees produced and a report on the Arts & Sciences Word Processing Center. Also includes enrollment figures and a letter from Professor Bell to Professor Arthur Kirsch about low enrollment
  - 1971; 1977 Arts and Sciences Chairman Handbook, 1 notebook (Box-folder 3:9)
    Manual that defines the responsibilities of various deans and officers as well as personnel policies and budget information
  - 1981-1982 Arts and Science Chairman Handbook, 1 notebook (Box-folder 3:10)
  - 1970-1985 Bayly Museum (University of Virginia Art Museum), 37 items (Box-folder 3:11)
    There are plans and policies of the museum and several drafts of a handbook. There is an inventory of objects that were cleaned. Correspondents include Frederick Hartt, (to President Edgar F. Shannon) David Summers, Malcolm Bell, Stephen Plog, and David Lawall
  - 1982-1983 Bayly Museum (University of Virginia Art Museum) Cyprus Pottery Controversy, 40 items (Box-folder 3:12)
    There are newspaper clippings and correspondence about a controversy in which the Bayly accepted a gift of ceramic pottery from the Turkish Federated State of Kibris. However the Republic of Cyprus claimed that the pottery belonged to them was not owned by the Turkish Federated State. Correspondents include UVA President Frank L. Hereford, Jr., Dr. Kenan Atakol, David B. Lawal, Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., Vamik D. Volkan, Edwin E. Floyd, Willard W. Harrison, Ambassador of Cyprus H. E. Andrew J. Jacovides, Richard H. Abbey (U. S. Chief Counsel of the Treasury) George G. Grattan, IV Legal advisor for the University, and Malcolm Bell. Other interested correspondents include Stephen G. Miller, Ellen Herscher, and Larry Ball. Included are photographs of the pottery.
  - 1970-1987 Book orders, 28 items (Box-folder 4:1)
    Book orders for art courses
  - 1985-1992 Budget and Space Committee, 16 items (Box-folder 4:2)
    Capital Project requests for the School of Architecture, Site Selection Subcommittee of the Master Plan Committee University of Virginia, space needs report for the Art Department, list of architecture firm proposals for the new Fine Arts Facility, Building Committees at the University of Virginia, and drawings of the Fine Arts Complex
  - 1986-1987 Classified Research Committee, 24 items (Box-folder 4:3)
    Included is correspondence from UVA President Robert O'Neil who assigned an ad hoc committee to study classified research. Also see Faculty minutes Box 5, Folder 2
  - 1980-1987 Committee on Residence Life, 22 items (Box-folder 4:4)
    Included is correspondence and reports on housing and dining areas for students. There is also information on Monroe Hill
  - 1988 Committee on Residence Life, 21 items (Box-folder 4:5)
    Included is a list of CORL members, correspondence and reports on housing and dining areas for students. There is also information on Monroe Hill and letters to President O'Neil about funding.
  - 1989 Committee on Residence Life, 39 items (Box-folder 4:6)
    There is correspondence and housing reports, and committee minutes on Pavillion VIII
  - 1983, 1988, 1989 Committee on Residence Life, 3 notebooks (Box-folder 4:7)
  - 1974-1980 University Correspondence, 30 items (Box-folder 4:8)
    Correspondents include I. B. Cauthen, Jr., W. Dexter Whitehead, Edwin E. Floyd, Robert M. MacLeod, Donald P Corderan, Daniel P. Edgar, Larry D. Craighead, John T. Casteen, Joseph F. Kett, Walter Hauser, Irvin Ehrenpreis, Kenneth Thompson, and Avery Catlin.
    Some topics include registration, personnel, class requirements, and computing services.
  - 1981-1989 University Correspondence, 57 items (Box-folder 4:9)
    Correspondents include Hans A. Schmitt, Martin Havran, William D. Sublette, Gilbert J. Sullivan, Javier Herrero, Frederick T. Kain, W. Dexter Whitehead, Henry Millon, Peter L. Munger, Roy Wagner, David T. Gies, Samuel P. Maroney, Jr., Merrill D. Peterson, Willard W. Harrison, Albert Whalley, Mark Morford, Murray Howard, Stephen Railton, John A. Blackburn, Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., John Humphrey, Hugh P. Kelly, Ray C. Hunt, Jr., Paul R. Gross, Ralph A. Lowry, Leonard Sandridge, Jon Mikalson, and Don E. Detmer. Topics include teaching assistants, recommendations for faculty to serve on committees, awards, budget, and a request from Bell to Dean Kelly for help in funding Morgantina
  - 1975-1982 University Correspondence Frank Hereford, 6 items (Box-folder 4:10)
    There are recommendations of faculty to serve on administrative committees, and suggestions from Professor Bell that the chairman of the art department also chair the Bayly Committee. There are also memos from University of Virginia President Frank L. Hereford and Vice President of Development John J. Owen about policies on solicitation and acceptance of gifts and bequests
  - 1986-1989 University Correspondence President Robert O'Neill, 16 items (Box-folder 4:11)
    There are letters from the President to the Faculty about new developments at the University. Topics and individuals mentioned include the end of Dean Edwin E. Floyd's term, the new term of Paul R. Gross, chairmanship of John A. Owen, Jr. and his task force on drug abuse, promotion of Leonard W. Sandridge to Executive Assistant to the President, Dr. Mueller, Mark Riesling on Afro-American Affairs, Henry J. Abraham and the Lawn, Bruce Nelson on the faculty handbook, appointments of Don E. Detmer, Shirley Menaker, John Scott, Eve Menger, W. James Copeland, Lincoln V. Lewis, Philip E. Nowlen, Jr., and Peter Hackett. Other topics include budget, research, women and salary inequities, new academic enhancement program, retirement options, student behavior, enrollment growth issues, online access to the library holdings, financial support for graduate students. There is also a list of University Committee members and correspondence between Professor Bell and the President about the importance of the Classics Department.
  - 1971-1974 University Educational Testing Material, 7 items (Box-folder 5:1)
    There is information about a new examination in the College Entrance Examinations on Art History. Included is a copy of the examination and correspondence about faculty helping the committee of reviewers by pretesting the exam
  - 1973-1988 University Faculty Senate Committee, 30 items (Box-folder 5:2)
    Included are the constitution, by-laws, goals and statement of purpose of the University, and a report on the Governor's budget. There are letters from Department Chairman Robert D. Cross on hiring procedures, and personnel policies. There are lists of committee members, and meeting minutes which mention that President Hereford was pleased with the selection of new President Robert O'Neil. Some of the topics included are the Honor System, Athletics, a conflict of interest for professors who authored their own textbooks, faculty relations, out of state tuition, undergraduates, student protests, faculty salaries, mandatory retirement age, enhancement of scholarship, and classified research.
  - 1982-1989 University Faculty Senate Planning Committee, 51 items (Box-folder 5:3)
    There are memos, reports (Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Budget Power Point Report) and minutes of their meetings about organizing the Faculty Senate and the University in terms of preserving teaching and research strengths, upgrading the quality of graduate programs and responding to specific initiatives made by the Governor.
  - 1973-1977 University Faculty Senate Policies, 17 items (Box-folder 5:4)
    There are explanations of procedures on tenure, promotion, and early retirement
  - 1974-1988 University Library at Fine Arts (Fiske Kimball), 28 items (Box-folder 5:5)
    There is correspondence between the University Library and the Fine Arts Library about circulation policies, reduced budget, missing books, and journals being unavailable to the Fine Arts Library. Fine Arts Faculty complained that these issues were affecting critical library functions.
  - n. d. University Library at Fine Arts (Fiske Kimball) Book lists from AJA, 20 items (Box-folder 5:6)
    There are photocopies of annotated lists from book catalogues (American Journal of Archaeology) with notations about whether the book was located at Alderman Library or the Fine Arts Library.
  - 1973-1977 University Personnel, 10 items (Box-folder 5:7)
    Forms and schedules for positions per enrollment figures
  - 1978-1988 University Regulations, 16 items (Box-folder 5:8)
    Included are regulations for travel regulations, promotion and tenure, worker's compensation, insurance, security, and student behavior (correspondence between Professor Bell and Dean of Students Robert Canevari about fraternities near the Bayly Museum)
  - 1965-1969; 1980-1988 University Renovations at Fine Arts Center, 18 items (Box-folder 5:9)
    Renovations and plans for a Fine Arts Center, (1965) renovations and repairs for Fayerweather Hall (1969; 1981) and information from the Carr's Hill Arts Complex Study Committee (1989) There is also budget information on the Governor's capital outlay requests, and justifications for the new art building.
  - Confidential
    - 1984 Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, 1 item (Box-folder 6:1)
      Draft of objectives
    - 1987 Correspondence student absences, 5 items (Box-folder 6:2)
    - 1977-1995 Grades, 28 items (Box-folder 6:3)
    - Oversize Grades, # items
      There are oversize print outs of student grades
    - 1988-1989 Grievances, 52 items (Box-folder 6:4)
    - 1974-1985 Positions and fellowships, 33 items (Box-folder 6:5)
      Includes resumes and letters about open positions and applying for fellowships (remove social security numbers)
    - 1963; 1974-1988 Promotions and tenure decisions, 18 items (Box-folder 6:6)
    - 1975-1989 Recommendations A-O, 60 items (Box-folder 6:7)
      Mostly there are letters of reference for students (written by Malcolm Bell)
    - 1973-1987 Recommendations P-Z, 7 items (Box-folder 6:8)
    - 1983; 1989 Salary Information, 4 items (Box-folder 6:9)
    - 1984 Search Committee for Dean of College, 27 items (Box-folder 6:10)
    - 1984; 1987-1988 Search Committee for Director of the University Press, 18 items (Box-folder 6:11)
      Included is correspondence from William Wright Abbot